<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-05T15:19:11+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Flâneurs’ Café</title><subtitle>Blog about the the art of flânerie.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Letter to the cities of Cracow &amp;amp; Płock</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-20-letter-cracow-plock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to the cities of Cracow &amp; Płock" /><published>2024-01-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/letter-cracow-plock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-20-letter-cracow-plock/">&lt;p&gt;Encouraged by Olga Harmsen—whom you can know from &lt;a href=&quot;https://aboutartnouveau.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;About Art Nouveau&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—I sent a letter to the officials in the cities of Płock and Cracow, as well as Museum Mazowieckie in Płocku and The National Museum in Cracow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the letter, I addressed similar issues as in my previous &lt;a href=&quot;../2024-01-16-letter-poznan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;letter to Miasto Poznań&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Most importantly, I have informed the authorities about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artnouveau-net.eu/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Réseau Art Nouveau Network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the upcoming webinar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Museum in Cracow has an interesting collection of works related to the Young Poland movement, and the Museum in Płock has a dependency devoted to Secession. For more information see the links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://muzeumplock.eu/oddzialy/kamienica-secesyjna/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Muzeum Mazowieckie Płock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mnk.pl/oddzial/mnk-wyspianski&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;MNK Wyspiański&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mnk.pl/oddzial/mnk-mehoffer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;MNK Mehoffer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will keep you posted regarding an eventual answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank &lt;a href=&quot;https://101010.pl/@AubreyDeLosDestinos&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aubrey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://venera.social/profile/brie/restricted&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for their comments and corrections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter can be downloaded here: &lt;a href=&quot;../uploads/2024-01-20-letter-cracow-plock/List_Secesja_Muzea-censored.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;List - Museums, cties, Cracow and Płock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credits for the image used for this post:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://pl.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plik:St._Francis_of_Assisi_Church,_interior-Stanis%C5%82aw_Wyspia%C5%84ski%27s_polichromy_%E2%80%9ENasturtiums%E2%80%9D,_2_Franciszka%C5%84ska_street,_Old_Town,_Krak%C3%B3w,_Poland.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;St. Francis of Assisi Church, interior-Stanisław Wyspiański’s polichromy „Nasturtiums”, 2 Franciszkańska street, Old Town, Kraków, Poland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>bperruche</name></author><category term="spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="history" /><category term="letters" /><summary type="html">Encouraged by Olga Harmsen—whom you can know from About Art Nouveau—I sent a letter to the officials in the cities of Płock and Cracow, as well as Museum Mazowieckie in Płocku and The National Museum in Cracow.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-20-letter-cracow-plock/wyspianski-church-polychrome.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter to the city of Poznań</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-16-letter-poznan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to the city of Poznań" /><published>2024-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/letter-poznan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-16-letter-poznan/">&lt;p&gt;Motivated by my recent visit to the city of my birth, Poznań and the upcoming webinar about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artnouveau-net.eu/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Réseau Art Nouveau Network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which will be organized on the first of February 2024 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.museovirasto.fi/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Museovirasto - Finnish Heritage Agency&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote a letter to the officials of the city of Poznań, Poland. At the turn of the 19th and 20th centuries, the city experienced economic and urban development preceded by deluge destruction in 1888. It also was relieved from a stronghold status that blocked any development before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city has a number of art nouveau buildings, usually in rather deplorable condition, with exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the letter, I informed the city about the recent revival of interest in Art Nouveau and also about the many steps the city could take in order to educate the rest of the world about its heritage as well as preserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter is in Polish, but feel free to translate it via Google if you would like to understand my message better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone attends the webinar and if by chance I will not be there, please let me know if someone from Poznań attended :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is as little or as much of what I can do today. I can only hope it will reach the appropriate people. I will keep you posted about the eventual answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to the information about the webinar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ssl.eventilla.com/artnouveauwebinar&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://ssl.eventilla.com/artnouveauwebinar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter can be downloaded here: &lt;a href=&quot;../uploads/2024-01-16-letter-poznan/list_secesja_poznan.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;List - Secesja w Poznaniu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>bperruche</name></author><category term="spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="history" /><category term="letters" /><summary type="html">Motivated by my recent visit to the city of my birth, Poznań and the upcoming webinar about Réseau Art Nouveau Network, which will be organized on the first of February 2024 by Museovirasto - Finnish Heritage Agency, I wrote a letter to the officials of the city of Poznań, Poland. At the turn of the 19th and 20th centuries, the city experienced economic and urban development preceded by deluge destruction in 1888. It also was relieved from a stronghold status that blocked any development before.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2024-01-16-letter-poznan/poznan-city-view.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Flâneur’s cities – what makes a city suitable for flânerie?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cities-of-flaneur/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flâneur’s cities – what makes a city suitable for flânerie?" /><published>2023-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cities-of-flaneur</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cities-of-flaneur/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The streets are narrow: “a maze of passages and streets which blur into each other and only become distinct near the quays of wood and lime.” The pavement is awful, leaving you having to negotiate puddles and mud: “Mud up to the ankles, sheets of water on the pavements poorly protected by asphalt.” In the evening the streets are badly lit and there is hardly anything to see and to do—&lt;strong&gt;Daniel Acke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When discussing cities and flânerie, we quickly arrive at a question: what makes a city suitable for a flâneur to thrive? In this essay, I will try to answer this question by analyzing “The Flâneur in Brussels: French and Belgian Literary Perspectives in Counterpoint” by Daniel Acke &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;2 (Chapter XIV)&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;. In his analysis, Acke examines literary texts about flânerie in Brussels. The first part of Acke’s analysis comprises works written by experienced Parisian flâneurs: Baudelaire, Narval, and Huysmans, who visited Brussels around the end of the XIX century. These authors are pessimistic in their tone, with Baudelaire being significantly negative, if not insulting. From these three accounts, one could conclude that flânerie in the Belgium capital was an impossible task. I agree with Daniel Acke that the principal reason why these texts show Brussels as the opposition to Paris of the time is that these authors were Parisian flâneurs. Indeed, they looked at the Belgium capital from the point of view of what they already knew and were used to, namely, Haussmannian Paris – a city with which, at the time, not many other cities could match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I think some of the points made by these authors are interesting and allow for a more general discussion about the characteristics that make a city suitable for practicing flânerie. Some of these are rather not obvious at first sight, and the reason for that is mainly rooted in changes that happened between when the texts were written and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have divided these characteristics into geographic, urban, and social classes. It is easy to see that many of these characteristics depend on each other, and I will highlight some of such dependencies. But let’s have a look at the classes collected in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Characteristic&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Class&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;topography&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;geographic&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;how hilly is the city&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;location&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;geographic&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;access to, e.g., rives, climate, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;sociability&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;social&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;population engagement in social activities&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;space&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;urban&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;size, crowdedness, but also view distance to architectural elements&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;amenities&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;urban&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;for example, existence and state of pavements, parks, squares, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;aesthetics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;urban&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;aesthetics of architecture&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;geographic-setting&quot;&gt;Geographic setting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In “The Flâneur in Brussels: French and Belgian Literary Perspectives in Counterpoint” by Daniel Acke &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;2 (Chapter XIV)&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt; there are two main motives that we can identify as of a geographic nature. The first is the topography, which is discussed in the context of Brussels being a hilly city and Paris is mainly flat. The other one is somewhat enigmatic for us today. Still, all Parisian flâneurs mention that in contrast to Paris, Brussels is not located at any significant waterway and saw that as an important drawback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;topography-and-enjoyable-walking&quot;&gt;Topography and enjoyable walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the accounts of the Parisian flâneurs, Brussels is described as a city not suitable for enjoyable strolling. This argument stems from an assumption made by the flâneurs of the past that walking should not be burdened with a physical effort. At least one of these authors admits that there are lovely views from the hills, but in his opinion, that cannot compensate for the effort needed to walk the streets in Brussels. In my opinion and experience as someone who lived in a very hilly city – Haifa, the topographic argument alone does not rule out a flânerie in a hilly city. Walking in a flat city may be effortless, but the hills add to the experience. Yet, it is true that a hilly city may make flânerie difficult for some people, e.g., the elderly or disabled. It is also quite clear that this characteristic is strongly connected to &lt;em&gt;amenities&lt;/em&gt; available in the city, such as sidewalks, shortcuts such as over hill stairs, cable cars, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sociability-encouraging-landmarks&quot;&gt;Sociability encouraging landmarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following and somewhat cryptic argument against flânerie in Brussels is that the city is not located around any major waterway. Narval wrote &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;2 (Chapter XIV)&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;there is no great city without a river&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, on that matter, we need to clarify one detail. As not many people may know that Paris has a second river – &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bi%C3%A8vre_(river)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;la Bièvre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; then probably equally few know that there is a small river passing through Brussels, and called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covering_of_the_Senne&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Senne&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Unfrotunently, both rivers faced a similar fate. Due to their pollution, they have been included in the sewer system and diverted. In the distant past, the Senne river, even if small, played the role of the main waterway to Brussels. Nevertheless, that was not the case in the XIX century because the pollution posed a significant health risk for the city’s population, as did la Bièvre in Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is a bit mysterious. It took me a while to understand why the lack of a river was such an essential argument against Brussels. But to understand that point, we need to travel in time to XIXth century Paris. Contrary to today, the banks of the Seine river were a bustling place. In fact, as strange as it may sound, life is returning to the banks of the Seine only recently. After WWII, we observed a decline in this part of the city being used as a social space, and around the 1970s, the banks were transformed into car roads. But let’s return to the XIX century.
Back then, the Seine’s banks were a place where all the social classes of the city collided. There were boats used for transporting people between different parts of the city (in some cases, it was the fastest way of commuting). We had the laundry boats and commercial activities such as goods being transported to the city. Before, even water-related industries occupied the banks, but they have pushed away during the Haussmann times. As we see, the banks of the Seine river were a place where a flâneur could observe and see through the different layers of the social classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I inserted a photo showing a painting by Thomas Shotter Boys (1803–1874) entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/boys-the-seine-and-palace-of-the-tuileries-t00966&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Seine and Palace of the Tuileries”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In the piece we can see boats, people doing laundry and, in the distance, other people involved in a sort of social activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;uk-margin-medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/uploads/post-haussmann-paris/T00966_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thomas Shotter Boys (1803–1874) entitled “The Seine and Palace of the Tuileries. Creative Commons CC-BY-NC-ND (3.0 Unported)&quot; /&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the real problem of Brussels was not a lack of a big river passing through the city. I think that the Parisian flâneurs would have probably also complained about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manzanares_(river)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manzanares river&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Madrid. Yet, as we leaned from the previous article &lt;a href=&quot;../art-of-flanerie/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Art of Flânerie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, flânerie was possible in Madrid but in a different form than in Paris. One factor that I think is important here is the sociability of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sociability&quot;&gt;Sociability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another vital part of the flânerie relates to how social aspects of the city’s population. As we learn from the accounts mentioned in the Acke text, people living in Brussels are somewhat individualistic. They prefer limiting their social interactions to their families and close peers. Acke quotes Joris-Karl Huysmans, who visited Brussels and wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The square is black, the avenues deserted, all the life of Brussels retreats to the place de la Monnaie and in the Galeries Saint-Hubert. … with the help of what potions, what opiated balms, could one succeed in putting an end to the interminable evening?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also quote here an account of Narval:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No shop window displays.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Flânerie past shops, this pleasure, this edification, an impossible thing!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Everyone stays home! (OC, 827). &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;2 (Chapter XIV)&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;role-of-climate-on-sociability&quot;&gt;Role of climate on sociability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among many possible explanations of the different behaviors in the inter-human interaction may play the climate.
A study from 2017 by Wei et al. &lt;a href=&quot;refTempPersonality&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt; found that the average ambient temperature closer to the psychological comfort temperature of 22°C contributes to personality threats that are associated with outdoor explorations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is particularly telling that our large datasets from two geographically large yet culturally distinct countries [China and the US] provided converging evidence. Taken together, these findings are consistent with our temperature clemency perspective of personality: growing up in temperatures that are close to the psychophysiological comfort optimum encourages individuals to explore the outside environment, thereby influencing their personalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors also mention an intriguing social thermoregulation theory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;which posits that people seek ‘social warmth’ in a cold environment because an important function of social relationships is to facilitate the regulation of body temperature. For example, a recent study found that, compared with residents of warmer climates, residents of colder climates reported a wider variety of social tie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this place, we can compare the climate between Paris and Brussels to see how different the weather is and whether such a difference can account for the social differences. Here I will include not only the temperatures but also two other factors that seem to me as plausible for being related to social behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average temperatures (Celsius) in Brussels and Paris &lt;a href=&quot;refWikiTemp&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jan&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Feb&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Mar&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Apr&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;May&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jun&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jul&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Aug&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sep&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Oct&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Nov&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Dec&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brussels&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paris&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absolute difference&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average monthly precipitation (in mm) for Brussels and Paris &lt;a href=&quot;refWikiPerci&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jan&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Feb&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Mar&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Apr&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;May&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jun&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jul&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Aug&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sep&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Oct&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Nov&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Dec&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brussels&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;61.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;69.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;65.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;72.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;73.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;76.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;69.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;848&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paris&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;41.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;49.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;62.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;52.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;61.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;57.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;637.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absolute difference&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20.4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;22.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25.9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;23.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;210.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunshine hours for Paris and Brussels &lt;a href=&quot;refWikiSunshine&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jan&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Feb&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Mar&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Apr&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;May&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jun&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Jul&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Aug&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sep&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Oct&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Nov&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Dec&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brussels&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;159&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;191&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;201&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;190&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;143&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;113&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1546&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Paris&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;166&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;202&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;168&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;68&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1662&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absolute difference&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;116&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the climate in Paris is slightly different than in Brussels; not only does Brussels have lower average temperatures and higher rainfall during the year, but more importantly receives significantly less sunshine. Unfortunately, the publication by Wei et al. &lt;a href=&quot;refTempPersonality&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt; does not include enough data for us to make any reasonable guesses about the impact of the above climate-related factors on the sociability of the populations living in Paris and Brussels. Generally speaking, such impacts are a fact, yet, we should remember that sociability is far more complex and does not solely depend on climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;urbanization&quot;&gt;Urbanization&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last key factor is the role of urbanization. I listed three items under the urban class in the first table: space, amenities, and aesthetics. The first relates to the size of the city and, for example, how much space one has while walking the streets – is there enough space to walk, or do we end up in overcrowded narrow streets?
The first one includes all the elements that improve or even allow for the experience of comfortable walking in the city. These are pavements, street lighting, parks, squares, passages, etc. As we read in the Acke, a Parisian flâneur visiting Brussels around the end of the XIX would find certain things unusual in comparison to Paris — a city that was undergoing significant urban changes at the time. In part about Huysmans’ visit to Brussels, we read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The pavement is awful, leaving you having to negotiate puddles and mud: “Mud up to the ankles, sheets of water on the pavements poorly protected by asphalt.” In the evening the streets are badly lit and there is hardly anything to see and to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it seems like Brussels lacked on space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;this distance seems to be sacrified in Brussels where people on the street come too close to each other &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;2 (Chapter XIV)&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason for that was purely related to urban planning and not in any aspect related to customs in the city. Indeed appreciation of monuments and gazing at shop windows also require space around the viewer. On crowded streets, one is disturbed and cannot focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other aspect of the city is its aesthetic, which, in my opinion, we can see twofold: architecture and other elements such as landscape. At the end of the XIX century, Brussels was full of monuments. But, in contrast to Haussmaniann Paris, it was a city without any particular architectural idea and rather chaotic in this aspect. To be fair, Leopold II tried to give the city a more Haussmaniann appearance, but that was later altered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;few-words-about-brusselization&quot;&gt;Few words about Brusselization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfornuently, Brussels has a relatively long history of “wars” with architecture and urban planning. For example, many of the buildings constructed by Leopold II were unfortunately replaced by modern ones around the 1960s. Some people went as far as calling Brussels ugly and chaotic &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[2 (Chapter XIV)]&lt;/a&gt;. This phenomenon of replacing old buildings with modern ones without any conceptions is known as Brusselization &lt;a href=&quot;#refWikiBrusselization&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;8&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt; and owes its name to the city of Brussels, and not without reason. To give you an example of the architectural and urban bonanza of Brussels, I inserted below illustrations showing: the famous Victor’s Horta “Maison du Peuple” – a building in the art nouveau style constructed in 1899 and demolished in 1965 (A) and figure (B) shows the &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Brussel,_Emile_Vanderveldenplein-PM_50988.jpg&quot;&gt;“Blaton Tower”&lt;/a&gt; that was constructed in the place of the “Maison du Peuple”. Worth noting is that the demolition of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maison_du_Peuple,_Brussels#/media/File:Maison_du_Peuple_of_the_P.O.B._(Belgian_Workers_Party)_(destroyed,_Brussels),_exterior_3_(cropped).jpg&quot;&gt;“Maison du Peuple”&lt;/a&gt; caused an outcry and protests, yet the city officials reminded indifferent to these voices &lt;a href=&quot;#refWikiMaisonDePeuple&quot;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;9&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;uk-margin-medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/uploads/brussels/maison_de_peuple_before_after.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;(A) – View of the Maison du Peuple/Volkshuis in the late 19th century or early 20th century (photo colorized with: imagecolorizer.com), and (B) – Blaton Tower on the spot where the Maison du Peuple stood until its demolition in 1965.&quot; /&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I am unsure whether aesthetics or any other aspect alone can dismiss a city as unsuitable for flânerie. Yet, architectural aesthetics can play a crucial role in our experience. Moreover, even if the city has exciting aesthetics but lacks, e.g., space, we will not be able to appreciate the aesthetics as we will not be able to stand in the best viewing position or be disturbed by bypassers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-thought&quot;&gt;The final thought&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we see, it is all complicated. Many of the identified by me factors are interconnected, e.g., lack of space will impact our appreciation of aesthetics. The cold climate will likely prevent us from exploring the city or stop us from making social observations as street life will be affected, etc. I think what is important here is that even if a city cannot change its climate or topography, it can still change many other things such as aesthetics, amenities, or space, and thanks to that, improve not only the experience of flânerie but also the life of the inhabitants. The last question I cannot answer right now is whether urban planning can alter sociability. My guess is that it is possible in a limited way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not seem easy to untangle the different contributors, and I think all of them need to be balanced to provide a great experience. While working on this essay, I talked about Brussels with a French colleague who lived in the city not long ago. In his opinion, Brussels city center today is more enjoyable to walk around than overcrowded Paris. Indeed, nowadays, in the view of many inhabitants, Paris is a great city to visit but not to live in due to the constant stress factor. As someone who spent around five years in the Parisian region, I have to say that I was glad to move from Paris to Haifa. It may seem weird to someone who visited Haifa on a day trip. Still, it is a calm place full of hidden gems which are impossible to find or appreciate in a short time – one of them being the people living in Haifa, who are incredibly sociable, most likely due to the sunny weather by a greater part of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baldus É. (circa 1860). Pont de Solférino (The header photo, colorized by imagecolorizer.com). Vergue. Retrieved January 15, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vergue.com/post/353/Pont-de-Solferino&quot;&gt;http://vergue.com/post/353/Pont-de-Solferino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;Wrigley, R. (Ed.). (2014). The Flâneur abroad: Historical and international perspectives. Cambridge Scholars Publishing.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refTurcot2015&quot;&gt;Turcot, L. (2015). The rise of the promeneur: walking the city in eighteenth-century Paris. Historical Research, 88(239), 67-99.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refTempPersonality&quot;&gt;Wei, W., Lu, J. G., Galinsky, A. D., Wu, H., Gosling, S. D., Rentfrow, P. J., … &amp;amp; Wang, L. (2017). Regional ambient temperature is associated with human personality. Nature Human Behaviour, 1(12), 890-895. (For online preview see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-017-0240-0.epdf?referrer_access_token=F8gHPevXyNpeVCheC2KoctRgN0jAjWel9jnR3ZoTv0N0D7_QaUTgihYYa1uPN_mbllanUjLBXnk9h-DSZaek6D3zaf04pTzgEXAGALsVj9n05OTZYmEQfFwZL8it6tDaM_rV25jwr6J_7PxdV3NJu1O3-fIjg5cX3eqUTDIeSM6tqdVCjRSOk547VVG8zsr1h44kowx0NjzqD6gzLaDzgT6yN-mldOkgoM0ZsEyDzcxAmSlUdxuN_JdHtocKNZW2fjeh1Gm7arfaD1Y095u1sBbkt5VlS2hrcvTySNaR0402Z7E2EpwqIvPAmd3sAnVEvn8lGGLwNFEYazjPBe5IkbIJ5p0PYyqxHG3wlkKhB9bQaS9f2uhXMToaLyNxfc4k&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWikiTemp&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. (2023, January 20). List of cities by average temperature. Wikipedia. Retrieved January 21, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_average_temperature&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_average_temperature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWikiPerci&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. (2023a, January 20). List of cities by average precipitation. Wikipedia. Retrieved January 21, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_average_precipitation&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_average_precipitation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWikiSunshine&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. (2022, November 13). List of cities by sunshine duration. Wikipedia. Retrieved January 21, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_sunshine_duration&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cities_by_sunshine_duration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWikiBrusselization&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. (2022a, September 3). Brusselization. Wikipedia. Retrieved January 22, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brusselization&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brusselization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWikiMaisonDePeuple&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. (2022a, August 12). Maison du Peuple, Brussels. Wikipedia. Retrieved January 22, 2023, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maison_du_Peuple,_Brussels&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maison_du_Peuple,_Brussels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>bperruche</name></author><category term="spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="history" /><category term="flânerie" /><summary type="html">The streets are narrow: “a maze of passages and streets which blur into each other and only become distinct near the quays of wood and lime.” The pavement is awful, leaving you having to negotiate puddles and mud: “Mud up to the ankles, sheets of water on the pavements poorly protected by asphalt.” In the evening the streets are badly lit and there is hardly anything to see and to do—Daniel Acke</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/post-haussmann-paris/seine-04859u-colorized-low-res.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Art of Flânerie</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/art-of-flanerie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Flânerie" /><published>2023-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/art-fl%C3%A2nerie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/art-of-flanerie/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Never have I thought or experienced, been more myself than when walking alone. There is something about walking which animates and enlivens my ideas; when immobile I am hardly capable of thought, to set my mind in motion I must first get my body moving. Country views, a succession of pleasant prospects, good air, the good appetite and good health that I gain by walking, the ease of the outdoor cabaret, far away from everything which makes me feel my dependence—&lt;strong&gt;Jean-Jacques Rousseau&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social and urban changes of the late XVIII and throughout the XIX century emerged a new class of city dwellers who enjoyed exploratory strolls through cities. This new type of city beings had been named flâneur, from the French verb flâner, which itself is of Nordic origin &lt;a href=&quot;#refDefFlaner&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Providing a precise translation is rather complicated, if not impossible, as many have already argued. Still, the closest English equivalent is the word stroller – a person who is enjoying a slow, relaxed walk &lt;a href=&quot;#refDefStroller&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. As we will see later, flâneur is an explorer, a philosopher of the streets – someone who observes and notices what others seem to overlook. Therefore, the world stroller does not consist of a one-to-one replacement as it strips the flâneur of a deeper meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With time the meaning of the word flâneur obtained extensions appropriate to the social, urban, and technological changes. These are, for example, digital flâneur. In this article, I will not focus on these more contemporary concepts. In this post, I will focus on the past and the art of walking. Indeed, in this first article, I will touch on the idea of flânerie – the art of city exploration. In the following articles, I will then try to answer whether the classical art of flânerie is a dead concept in modern cities that tend to be polluted with cars and uncontrolled tourism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-pinch-of-history&quot;&gt;A pinch of history&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary motivation behind the way the city has been explored and walked through has been connected to the urban arrangement of the cities. The medieval like-cities, such as Paris before the Haussmannian restoration (which started in the 1850s and was finally concluded in 1927), were often places where one would not find any pleasure wandering about. Indeed, the pre-Hausmannian Paris was a maze of shady, narrow, crowded streets, often filled with litter. The old, sometimes medieval buildings were not adapted to the ever-growing population. In short, Paris before the 1850s was not a city where living was enjoyable. Let me use for an illustration of the situation the following quote from Victor Considerant &lt;a href=&quot;#refdeMoncan2002&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paris is an immense workshop of putrefaction, where misery, pestilence and sickness work in concert, where sunlight and air rarely penetrate. Paris is a terrible place where plants shrivel and perish, and where, of seven small infants, four die during the course of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also read that in 1739 Voltaire wrote to the King of Prussia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I saw the fireworks which they fired off with such management; would rather they started to have a Hôtel de Ville, beautiful squares, magnificent and convenient markets, beautiful fountains, before having fireworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not have a source of that quote at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a similar picture could have been drawn based on other cities at the time in Europe. Yet to give you a better understanding of the problem, let me tell you that there is a second river passing by Paris called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bi%C3%A8vre_(river)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;la Bièvre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#refMarvilleNGA&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. This tributary of the Seine during the Haussmann work was put into the city’s sewer system. The reason behind it was simple – pollution from the local tanneries, which operated in the city until they were banned during restoration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;uk-margin-medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/uploads/art-of-flanerie/marville-bievre.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Bièvre River (fifth arrondissement), c. 1862
albumen print from collodion negative Joy of Giving Something, Inc.&quot; /&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many associate the appearance of flâneur with the Haussmannian renovation of Paris and claim that flâneur could not possibly emerge before the renovation or in another city than Paris. Yet the trends started to change earlier even in Paris after the demolition of the city walls and the creation of the first boulevards during the reign of Louis XIV at the end of the XVII century &lt;a href=&quot;#refTurcot2015&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, researchers studying the topic have discovered that similar types of city explorers have occurred before or at the same time in other cities such as, for instance, London and Madrid &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The figure below is an engraving by Pellicer, which illustrates walkers on the Puerta del Sol square in Madrid around 1876.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;uk-margin-medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/uploads/art-of-flanerie/grabado-pellicer.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Walkers in the [*Puerta del Sol*](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puerta_del_Sol) on any given afternoon in 1876. Engraving by Pellicer. The Spanish and American Enlightenment&quot; /&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in each city where the art of walking the streets was practiced, one could identify differences. Let’s dig into, e.g., Madrid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What happens in Spain’s main city does not occur in any other promenades [in Berlin, Constantinople, London, and Paris]. The person who goes to the Tuileries, only goes to stroll, to listen to the music played every afternoon by the military bands; if they run into an acquaintance, they are surprised. In Spain’s promenades, one of the most attractive features - if not the main attraction - is the fact that one will find friends or acquaintances. If this only occurred in the provinces, it would not be remarkable, but it also happens in Madrid. &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[3 (see p. 155 and footnote 56 therein)]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, flânerie could not be or, in a limited sense, be enjoyed in some cities such as Brussels &lt;a href=&quot;#refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;[3] (see Chapter XIV)&lt;/a&gt;. The question is, then, what kind of attributes must a city possess to be suitable for flânerie? Let us leave this question for another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, what is essential to note in this place is the fact that one of the main differences between the past and now is the fact that people of all classes and genders can now enjoy flânerie, which was not the case in the past, for example, the social standards imposed on woman, which limited their ability to become a flâneur, flâneuese or passante, with the two later being female versions of the word flâneur with passante coined by Marcel Proust and flâneuese being introduced by scholars in the XXI century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will finish the article here and leave the exploration of the details for another time. In the next posts, I will try to focus on the two following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the art of flânerie dead?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what makes a city suitable for a flânuer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refDefFlaner&quot;&gt;Définitions : flâner. (n.d.). In Dictionnaire De Français Larousse. Retrieved December 27, 2022, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/flâner/34028&quot;&gt;https://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/flâner/34028&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refDefStroller&quot;&gt;Definition: stroller. (n.d.). Oxford Dictionary. Retrieved December 27, 2022, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com/definition/english/stroller?q=stroller&quot;&gt;https://www.oxfordlearnersdictionaries.com/definition/english/stroller?q=stroller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refWrigley2014&quot;&gt;Wrigley, R. (Ed.). (2014). The Flâneur abroad: Historical and international perspectives. Cambridge Scholars Publishing.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refMarvilleNGA&quot;&gt;Charles Marville: Photographer of Paris. (n.d.). National Gallery of Art. Retrieved December 27, 2022, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2013/marville.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/2013/marville.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refdeMoncan2002&quot;&gt;De Moncan, P., &amp;amp; Heurteux, C. (2002). Le Paris d’Haussmann. Editions du Mécène.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refTurcot2015&quot;&gt;Turcot, L. (2015). The rise of the promeneur: walking the city in eighteenth-century Paris. Historical Research, 88(239), 67-99.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>bperruche</name></author><category term="spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="history" /><category term="flânerie" /><summary type="html">Never have I thought or experienced, been more myself than when walking alone. There is something about walking which animates and enlivens my ideas; when immobile I am hardly capable of thought, to set my mind in motion I must first get my body moving. Country views, a succession of pleasant prospects, good air, the good appetite and good health that I gain by walking, the ease of the outdoor cabaret, far away from everything which makes me feel my dependence—Jean-Jacques Rousseau</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/art-of-flanerie/HIGH_ST_SOUTHEND_WITH_GARONS_CINEMA_&amp;_SHOPS_postcard_ESSEX.jpg" /></entry></feed>